Good morning, my name is Dan Margulies and I'm filling in for
Rabbi Linter while he is on vacation for the next few days.
We are on נדרים מ"ה, Nedarim Mem Hei, and because it's such
a short דף, daf, we're going to first touch on a few
other small topics that we were left with at the end of
the previous פרק perek and then we're going to start new פרק,
perek, פרק השותפין. Perek Hashutfim. So if that's alright, we'll start with
that.
Morning, morning.
All right, so where we left off was we had a מחלוקת
machlokes between רבי יוסי Reb Yosi and רבנן Rabbanan about how does
הפקר hefker work, and we had a מחלוקת machlokes in the אמוראים
Amora'im about how to understand how רבי יוסי Reb Yosi would apply,
and we had some different sources, ברייתא beraisa and another משנה mishna
I think. And so from there, I want to talk a little
bit about what, how does הפקר hefker work in general just because
we have such a short דף daf to do today, we can
spend a little bit more time on some of the ideas. So
the first is just to note that
הפקר... hefker... you can record from here also, okay sure thing.
Okay, so the first is that the case from the משנה mishna
was that a person had been מודר הנאה mudar hana'ah from another
person and decided to put the food on a rock, right? And
be מפקיר mafkir the food so that it's not his anymore and
then he'd be able to get הנאה hana'ah from it. The question
really becomes well what is this הפקר? hefker? If הפקר hefker actually
gets rid of the prohibition that stems from ownership or not because
maybe there are two different types of הפקר hefker or two different
ways we can look at how הפקר hefker works. One would be
that it gives you permission to actually gives permission to other people
to use it but doesn't necessarily give up your ownership until somebody
else acquires it. So in that limbo period when the first person
has been מפקיר mafkir until another person has stepped in and it's
kind of floating in limbo, maybe the original ownership is still there
and then the נדר neder would still be in effect if it's
about, if the נדר neder is dependent on ownership. So that wouldn't
really fit to explain the משנה, mishna, so that would be a
challenge to understand how רבי יוסי's Reb Yosi explanation would work with
that.
Another point is that actually the רמב"ם Rambam I think Rabbi Rosenkopf
maybe mentioned this yesterday, the רמב"ם Rambam notes that in a certain
sense הפקר hefker is a kind of נדר. neder. It's a bit
different kind but in a certain sense it's your words are changing
the status of this object. In this case the way הפקר hefker
works is that it changes the ownership of the object, but in
a certain sense it's a kind of הפקר hefker is a kind
of נדר. neder. If that's the case then
some
of the other rules that we know about נדרים nedarim would apply
as well, things that we've seen. For example the גמרא gemara on
דף ז' daf zayin which was a few weeks back, the גמרא
gemara in נדרים nedarim on דף ז' daf zayin talks about how
does יד yad work for הפקר, hefker, is there יד להפקר yad
l'hefker or not? And so again that's a comparison between נדרים nedarim
and הפקר. hefker. That maybe the רמב"ם's Rambam source, it's not clear
sort of why the רמב"ם Rambam made this necessarily made this suggestion.
But another great example would be what happens if a person makes
something הפקר hefker and then dies? If it were a קניין, kinyan,
if it's a real transfer of ownership to no one and then
someone else can come along, then the הפקר hefker presumably should work
even if you pass away in between. But if הפקר hefker is
something more like a נדר, neder, well if you pass away your
descendants, your inheritors do not have any obligation to fulfill your נדרים
nedarim for you and therefore if a person made something הפקר, hefker,
I say my house is הפקר hefker then I drop dead,
then the descendants, my descendants would not need to treat the house
as הפקר, hefker, it would fall back into the inheritance because it
never really left my ownership, it was just I had tried to
change it with some kind of a נדר. neder. And so that
would be another example of something that, in which הפקר hefker is
similar to נדרים. nedarim.
You actually call it a נדר? neder?
He says it's similar to נדרים nedarim I think, I have to
check the לשון lashon exactly.
As far as your language is changing something?
Right, cause you say this is just like saying this is קונם,
konam, you would say this is הפקר. hefker. So you're using words
to change the status of the object. The status that you're changing
is not whether it's אסור assur or מותר, mutar, but it's whether
it belongs to you or belongs to someone else.
Does it fit with תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros the same thing as
that? Because that changes the status of it
also.
Well for sure all of these different kinds of speech acts are
very similar and have some overlap and some similarities and some differences
as well. So with separating out תרומה terumah and מעשר, maaser, you
know you're taking some kind of forbidden food, טבל, tevel, which again
the question in the אחרונים acharonim I think or even in the
ראשונים rishonim becomes with תרומה, terumah, is טבל tevel the untithed produce
which then you remove the תרומה terumah from, is that... טבל Tevel
all along was really just a mixture of תרומה Terumah and חולין
Chullin together and you're just taking off the תרומה Terumah part. That's
going to touch on something that we're doing today actually. Or is
טבל Tevel its own category? טבל Tevel is untithed and the act
of tithing creates תרומה Terumah and creates the חולין Chullin through the
act of separation.
It has the same thing about the creation story when God separates
light and darkness and water and land.
It has a נדר. neder.
Okay, so again the comparison to a נדר neder is the fact
that you're using a speech act to change the status of an
object. It's on the חפצא, Heftza, it's something that's been touched on
throughout the מסכתא. masechta. Different
than thinking broadly.
And again there might be halakhic similarities or there might not in
different cases. Okay
fine. So one other point about הפקר Hefker is the principle of
הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker Beit Din Hefker which came up as
well which is that in the discussion of whether you need three
people for making something הפקר Hefker or not and the גמרא Gemara
makes a suggestion right at the end of מה עמוד א Mem
He Amud Alef that אחד הוי, Echad Havi, so
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi disagrees with רבי שמעון
בן הוצדק. Rabbi Shimon Ben Hotzadak. רבי שמעון בן הוצדק Rabbi Shimon
Ben Hotzadak said כל המפקיר בפני שלושה הוי הפקר, Kol Hamaphkir Bifnei
Shlosha Havi Hefker, if you make something הפקר Hefker in front of
three people then it is הפקר. Hefker. בפני שניים לא הוו הפקר
Bifnei Shnayim Lo Havu Hefker but if it's in front of two
people it's not הפקר. Hefker. Oh, so it sounds like it's a
difference between something that needs עדות edut witnesses two witnesses only and
three is usually a בית דין, Beit Din, right?
And
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi says דבר תורה אפילו
באחד הוי הפקר Devar Torah Afillu Beachad Havi Hefker even one person
counts as
הפקר. Hefker. ומה טעם אמרו בשלושה Uma Taam Amru Bishlosha why did
the rabbis then impose a standard that you need to be מפקיר
maphkir in front of three people? כדי שיהיה אחד זוכה ושניים מעידים
Kedai Sheyihiyeh Echad Zocheh Ushnayim Me'idim because one person can acquire it
and two people will be the witnesses. Okay so that's a different
model. So now let's think. Number one, רבי שמעון בן הוצדק Rabbi
Shimon Ben Hotzadak at least at face value sounds like maybe you
need a בית דין Beit Din but not not two witnesses. Alternatively
he's not talking about בית דין Beit Din at all. He's talking
about you just need something public more than just two witnesses. As
Ben Franklin quipped three can keep a secret if two of them
are dead. So when three people know about something it's public. It
will become revealed and in the ר"ן's Ran לשון lashon it's אבשא
מילתא avsha milta which is a public thing or it's loud enough
to be well known. There's an idea of קול, kol, certain certain
rumors develop standing in the public sphere once a few people know
about them. With לשון הרע lashon hara once a few people know
about it three people know about it then it becomes something which
has a different status. And so that may be what רבי שמעון
בן הוצדק Rabbi Shimon Ben Hotzadak is talking about not even a
בית דין. Beit Din. So what about a בית דין? Beit Din?
הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker Beit Din Hefker we say that if
a בית דין Beit Din makes property הפקר Hefker then the property
is הפקר, Hefker, it's ownerless. The בית דין Beit Din has that
power. That comes up in a few different places. One of the
interesting examples off the top of my head is with קידושין Kiddushin
which we're coming up to in a few months. So
קידושין Kiddushin there's certain cases very limited cases again it was a
topic of big political debate a few decades ago about the סוגיא
sugya of אפקיעינהו רבנן לקידושי מיניה afkinu rabanan lekiddushei minei that the
rabbis under very certain circumstances have the power to annul marriages. And
at least in some of the ראשונים rishonim the mechanism by which
that would work is that the money that you used for the
קידושין Kiddushin the ring or whatever would retroactively the בית דין Beit
Din can declare that that money was never really yours it was
הפקר. Hefker. So that's the power of הפקר בית דין הפקר. Hefker
Beit Din Hefker. And the גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin deals with
the source for הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker Beit Din Hefker and
there are two possible sources with very different implications for how it
works. The first source is the division of the נחלה. nachalah. When
the Jewish people came into the land of Israel they divided the
land by גורל goral by lottery. Okay so wait a second. Once
I make I get my lottery trip and I know which field
is mine how
did
I acquire that? How did we were all the Jewish people arriving
in the land of Israel everyone has a certain portion in the
land and then now I'm only everyone sort of owns the whole
thing jointly which we're going to touch on a little bit as
well.
No one owns anything השם Hashem owns it and השם Hashem gave
it to them.
Okay so that becomes something of a שמיטה Shmitta is about.
Okay so the way then that
הפקר Hefker so that becomes the source for הפקר בית דין הפקר
Hefker Beit Din Hefker according to one opinion that in dividing the
land the rabbis employed this mechanism that they can take something away
from you make it ownerless and then designate to whom it now
belongs. That means that הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker Beit Din Hefker
is not only making something ownerless but can even be a transfer
of ownership.
Who's it being transferred to?
It's transferred from the collective ownership into a specific person. This plot
of land now belongs to David or Bill
or יהושע. Yehoshua.
As you can imagine, the entire land was owned jointly.
No, I don't imagine that. How was the entire land owned jointly?
Because everyone owns the whole land as the Jewish people. Okay, so
when we get to גיטין, Gittin, I'm sure we'll go through that.
Okay, the other source is a source from עזרא. Ezra. Source from
עזרא Ezra says that as a punishment for people who didn't come
into the land, that the בית דין Beis Din had the power
to make their property חרם, cherem, to take it away. Okay, so
two possibilities. The first source sounds like בית דין Beis Din is
basically in charge of the property. Whether it's because it really belongs
to God and בית דין Beis Din are some kind of administrators,
whether the בית דין Beis Din fundamentally has power over the land.
It's almost sort of a joint ownership model. The government owns everything
and they can sort of tell you, okay, fine, you can use
this for now. I mean, again, this is touching on similar ideas
to, you know, when people write להו lamed-hey-vav in their ספרים seforim
and things like that. לה' הארץ ומלואה, L'Hashem ha-aretz umlo'ah, that God
owns everything. And so if God owns everything, then God can take
it away, God can tell you to do certain things with it.
So the בית דין Beis Din here can take it from you
and give it to someone else. So that's the בית דין Beis
Din basically owns everything. That's option number one. The second one is
a bit different. The second one is more sort of policing rights.
The בית דין Beis Din can fine you, the בית דין Beis
Din can take away your property when you've done something wrong. So
the first is communal ownership, the government is in charge of everything,
and the second is the government has policing rights. Those are two
very different models of how the בית דין Beis Din functions, what
is הפקר בית דין הפקר, Hefker Beis Din Hefker, and thinking about
governmental systems that the תורה Torah is prescribing.
Okay, a peculiar type of
socialism.
A peculiar type of socialism indeed.
Ayn Rand would not be happy. So, I mean to me, it
seems like the whole model was clarifying parts of the גורל. goral.
We're going to get to clarifying, that's our next משנה. mishna.
That's what the גורל goral does.
Okay, so we'll take a look there in just a second. But
it's a great point.
Yes, does the government take land for its own use from someone?
So that becomes an interesting question. There are cases, for example, the
king can claim certain land to make a road or to do
different things to set up army camps.
And those are also rules that were just set up by יהושע
Yehoshua when יהושע Yehoshua conquered the land. There are certain, I think
they're like eight different sort of common property law rules that יהושע
Yehoshua set up. It's in the רמב"ם Rambam as well, it's in
the גמרא, Gemara, about sort of you have a public easement through
your field, there's a footpath that everyone uses, and how much space
does that get to take up, and how wide are the roads
and different kinds of things like that. Who gets to graze their
animals in different places?
So those are again those public land use, public land use questions
that come up. I think a lot of that is in the
גמרא Gemara in בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. So that'll be a year
from now or two years from now, right? Get there when you
get there. Okay,
just one other thing is about ביטול חמץ. Bitul Chametz. According to
תוספות, Tosafot, according to תוספות Tosafot on פסחים דף ב', Pesachim daf
bet,
the way ביטול חמץ Bitul Chametz works is in some way tied
up with הפקר. Hefker. It may not be that the act of
ביטול bitul is הפקר, hefker, it might be that the act of
ביטול bitul makes the חמץ chametz הפקר. hefker. But the prospect, the
idea of being מבטל mevatel your חמץ, chametz, making—nullifying your חמץ, chametz,
making it ownerless, according to תוספות Tosafot is something similar to הפקר.
hefker.
Then someone else acquires it, how does that work? How do you
like that other model?
Okay, so again, the way at least we use ביטול חמץ Bitul
Chametz is we do other things as well. But imagine a person
owns all their חמץ, chametz, whatever, and then a person says, "I'm
מבטל mevatel my חמץ, chametz, it's ownerless, I make it הפקר, hefker,
something like that." Then you leave all the Cheerios in the shelves,
you leave all the, you know, residue, grime on your frying pans,
everything like that, and you just you close the door, fine, done.
According to תוספות's Tosafot interpretation of how ביטול חמץ Bitul Chametz works,
the way the גמרא Gemara says it, that should at least that
should work fine.
We then rabbinically have imposed by the rabbis from the משנה mishna
searching for the חמץ, chametz, destroying the חמץ chametz actively, other kinds
of things. But ביטול, bitul, just nullifying it with your speech act
would be enough.
Yes, so we were discussing yesterday the idea of whether the person
still possesses it even after he makes it הפקר. hefker.
Exactly, that's the מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the
רבנן. rabbanan.
If we didn't have these other customs of burning and stuff like
that, what would happen? He'd just still possess it over פסח. Pesach.
First of all, he'd drop dead, it's in
his רשות.
reshut. He'd have
a big problem. Does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose also have the possibility
of recovering it if nobody else takes it after?
So this is at least part of רמב"ן's Ramban big critique of
תוספות Tosafot there in the beginning of פסחים דף ב'. Pesachim daf
bet. רמב"ן Ramban says, "I don't know what you're talking about, תוספות,
Tosafot, you got it all wrong. It can't be that ביטול חמץ
Bitul Chametz works by הפקר. hefker. It's a different mechanism. It's a
mechanism much more almost psychological." The רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban*'s explanation is that
ביטול חמץ chametz *bittul chametz* is something like ביטול עבודה זרה *bittul
avodah zarah*. It's that a person has decided, when a person worships
idols, right, whether or not a Jewish person, imagine a non-Jewish person
worships idols, and then says, you know what, this idol, it's not
doing it for me anymore, I'm going to go do something else
and chops off the head or chops off the ear of the
idol. Okay,
so that, or the idol breaks and he throws it in the
trash and says I'm going to go buy a new one. So
that's ביטול עבודה זרה *bittul avodah zarah*. The עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*,
the idol, has been nullified by some kind of process. It's not
about making it הפקר hefker, *hefker*, it's about saying for me or
or how I relate to this object has fundamentally changed. So that's
the way the רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* really deals with the question of
ביטול חמץ chametz *bittul chametz* is saying that you, I don't want
חמץ chametz *chametz* for a week, I'm trying to keep פסח Pesach,
*Pesach*, so that's that's the ביטול *bittul* of mine. I don't need
it. I, whether it's, he says אינו אני רוצה בקיומו *eino ani
rotzeh b'kiyumo*, I don't, I don't want to keep this, I don't
want to own this, I don't want this to exist anymore. And
again, so that's a very powerful statement. That's saying the fact that
you just don't want it is enough to
dissolve your relationship with this object, at least מדאורייתא mid'oraita *mide'oraita*. And
rabbinically, there are other mechanisms that were imposed because it seems so,
seems so easy.
No, but it's different עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*, like you know, the
whole point is that it is worshipped, right? So by me chopping,
you know, I'm showing that it's no longer an object of worship.
But what am I doing in חמץ chametz *chametz*? I'm just
throwing
out a bunch of words. So how does that, how does that
work in הלכה halakha *halacha*?
It's a big question. Again, how do, how why should it be
that the words would have the power to change the status of
the חמץ chametz *chametz*? And so the ר"ן Ran *Ran* in פסחים
*Psachim* there, same ר"ן Ran *Ran* hopefully, the ר"ן Ran *Ran* in
פסחים *Psachim* on דף א עמוד amud א *daf aleph amud aleph*
in the pages of the רי"ף *Rif*, right there at the beginning,
the ר"ן Ran. *Ran* says, well, חמץ chametz *chametz* is different because
חמץ chametz *chametz*, the תורה Torah *Torah* already said, the תורה *Torah*
already said בל יראה ובל ימצא *bal yera'eh u'val yimatzei*. The תורה
*Torah* said the two prohibitions that in a sense remove your power
or relationship to this חמץ *chametz*. You're not allowed to own חמץ
*chametz*, so the fact that you owned it, it's not really your
owning it anymore. It's that the תורה *Torah* said it's like you
own it in order that you should violate these two מצוות *mitzvot*.
Therefore, the only amount of ownership you have left is, is a
small kind of ownership, and then you would have a mechanism to
get rid of it that's maybe a weaker mechanism than would otherwise
work.
I'm sorry, wait, so the תורה *Torah* made it more strict, therefore
it's easier to get out of it?
The תורה *Torah* said, really you don't own it anymore. Really, this
is not yours anymore because there's a prohibition.
If you do nothing.
If you do nothing. The only,
the only way in which you own a חמץ *chametz* on פסח
Pesach *Pesach* is such that you violate the prohibition on owning חמץ
*chametz*. The תורה *Torah* put it into your ownership, and that's even
a לשון lashon *lashon* from the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says something like that. And so the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says,
ah, so I understand חמץ *chametz* is different, it's actually already out
of your רשות reshut, *reshut*, it's already been removed from my ownership,
and now there's just a smidge left of some connection and I
can dissolve that very easily. It's not like making my real property
הפקר hefker *hefker*.
Where the תורה *Torah* says it's not in your רשות *reshut*? It
says it should not be seen, which sounds like it's adding another
level.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* tries to learn it out from some
of the prohibitions of חמץ *chametz*, including תשביתו *tashbitu*, whether תשביתו *tashbitu*
is active or passive, and other things like that. Not for now,
פסחים *Psachim* it's a different tangent. Okay.
But no one explains how it works according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi *Rabbi Yose*? If you, if you operate according to הפקר hefker
*hefker* and you're רבי rebbe, יוסי *Rabbi Yose*, then it can't work,
right?
Well, again, not for now. All the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* are dealing
with רבנן rabbanan *rabbanan*, so they're not going to deal with רבי
rebbe יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. And again, it may be that, so the
רמב"ן *Ramban*, well it's not really הפקר hefker, *hefker* at all, and
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* would say, well it's a different הפקר hefker? *hefker*.
So that would be the way to solve it for רבי Rebbe
יוסי *Rabbi Yose*.
Wait, but that degree of loss of control is sufficient... under control.
Possession's a strong word, but it's control or something like
that.
So you're saying תוספות *Tosafot* says that it is הפקר hefker *hefker*,
but basically something like הפקר hefker, *hefker*, and תוספות *Tosafot* might still
back off and say it's a different הפקר hefker *hefker* than the
normal הפקר hefker, *hefker*.
Because again, just
because again, it's like you're saying. To change the relationship of this
object you still may retain some residual ownership afterwards like רבי Rebbe.
יוסי *Rabbi Yose* and things like that. If no one else comes
and claims it, you would be stuck. So it might not be
enough. So that's part of the רמב"ן *Ramban*'s critique of תוספות *Tosafot*.
And תוספות *Tosafot* would say, well this is actually different, right? So
תוספות *Tosafot* might follow a similar reasoning as the ר"ן Ran, *Ran*
and say the ownership that you have over this חמץ *chametz* is
not really a real ownership so you don't need a real הפקר
hefker. *hefker* in order to get rid of it. And there are
other other pieces at play. It's more tricky than that. Okay. Yeah.
One other observation, which is that if what we're talking about, we
said that the משנה mishnah *mishna* was dealing with a case of
what? The משנה mishnah *mishna* was dealing with a case of a
person was מפקיר *mafkir* the food and put it on a rock
so that the other person who didn't have any food could come
and get the food. The question is, I don't understand. If we're
talking about the fact that the הלכה halacha *halacha* follows רבי שמעון
בן לוי Rabbi Shimon ben Levi *Rabbi Shimon Ben Levi*.
That really דאורייתא deoraisa, אפילו באחד הוי הפקר, afilu be'echad havei hefker,
מדאורייתא mid'oraita it's okay to have only one person there for הפקר,
but even rabbinically we need three, and רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabbi
Shimon ben Yehotzadak says even מדאורייתא mid'oraita, you need three people there.
So according to either of these two opinions, how did the משנה
mishnah. work? It was just the two of them.
יהא הקלו לצורך זה yeha hiklu letzorech zeh because the guy's got
nothing to eat.
Okay, so the ריטב"א Ritva goes like what you're saying, the ריטב"א
Ritva says because it's בשעת הדחק, besha'at hadachak, it's a pressing situation,
this person has no food. Okay, so even if we say like
רבי שמעון בן לוי Rabbi Shimon ben Levi that there's a rabbinic
need for three, then still he's willing to allow it in a
case of one because of שעת הדחק. sha'at hadachak. We often see
that rabbinic laws don't apply in the same way in שעת הדחק.
sha'at hadachak.
Alternatively, one of the אחרונים achronim the מחנה אפרים Machaneh Ephraim says
that there's a difference between real estate קרקע karka and מטלטלין, metaltelin,
that food is movable objects, it's a sort of almost a weaker
kind of ownership and one would be enough because as soon as
I'm holding it, that's basically the core essence of what it means
to own it. So you put it down on the rock and
somebody else picks it up, well it's hefker. But with land there's
much more of a need, again this is the third פרק perek
of בבא בתרא Bava Batra deals a lot with how do you
really establish rights to a piece of land, whether you own it
or not, but how do you sort of make that claim at
least. There's much higher standard of ownership for land, well that needs
much more of a public announcement, even in American law you have
to file the deed with the city office, you have to do
this, you have to do this, it's not the same as just
going to buy a pack of chips from the supermarket. So land
might require three, and according to the מחנה אפרים, Machaneh Ephraim, even
according to רבי שמעון Shimon בן לוי Levi, one would be enough
even מדרבנן. mid'rabbanan. The only reason the rabbis imposed the need of
three for הפקר was actually only for land. Okay, one more point
is the כסף משנה Kesef Mishnah notes that according to the רא"ש,
Rosh, doing הפקר just by yourself, הפקר בינו לבין עצמו, hefker beino
levein atzmo, the רא"ש Rosh says it should work fine, and the
רמב"ם Rambam because he's referencing this גמרא Gemara that says באחד הוי
הפקר be'echad havei hefker מדאורייתא, mid'oraita that one would be enough,
so definitely
nobody holds according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, nobody holds that just by
yourself saying it's hefker works. Why? Because what have you done? You've
just talked to yourself and said you don't own it anymore, but
nobody else knows about it.
And that gets back to חמץ then.
It goes back to the similar point about the חמץ which is
if no
one's around when I say it or not?
Right. If nobody else knows that this object is הפקר, is it
really הפקר?
So that's exactly the point. If no one else knows that you've
given up your ownership, everyone else will think that you still own
it, so then it's the same as owning it.
And interestingly enough, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch paskens like the רא"ש
Rosh
in אורח חיים. Orach Chayim. The שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says that
by שביתת בהמתו, shevitat behemto, the prohibition on letting your animals work
on שבת, Shabbat,
that saying הפקר בינו לבין עצמו hefker beino levein atzmo by yourself
it would work in order to get your animal out of your
ownership so that if you've already lent your animal to someone who's
not Jewish and they want to use your animal to plow their
field on שבת, Shabbat,
then you're like oh my gosh, you get to be שבת Shabbat
morning you say he's going to go out and plow today, so
then you can say that it's הפקר just by yourself. However, in
חושן משפט... Choshen Mishpat...
and then you have to tell him it's hefker?
No, exactly. So that's why the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says like
the רא"ש Rosh there in אורח חיים. Orach Chayim. But in חושן
משפט Choshen Mishpat in dealing with all the property laws how it
applies to הפקר, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch seems to פסקן pasken
like the רמב"ם Rambam that it does need to be in front
of at least one person even מדאורייתא mi'deoraisa and then מדרבנן mid'rabbanan
three. Okay, now let us move on to the new פרק. perek.
Yes.
Okay, just aside from whether you need one, two, or three people
for a moment, the whole issue in the משנה mishna was really
when you're only with a person who is prohibited by נדר neder
from benefiting from your property and the whole idea of putting it
on the rock is a contrivance to get around the נדר. neder.
So we still haven't answered the question of whether הפקר really is
its own independent ownerless state or you still own it until the
other person takes possession. The question was whether you can do that
under those circumstances that person is prohibited from taking possession. So it
either is truly ownerless or it's not.
So the answer would be at least the way we saw it
was that there was a מחלוקת machloket in the תנאי, tannai, רבי
יוסי and the other rabbis, and there were other sources brought as
proofs. It sounds like at least the הלכה halacha should follow רבנן
that this principle works because that's who it's working for in the
משנה. mishna.
There may be actually I think if I remember correctly I don't
want to find it now, I think somewhere in the ר"ן Ran,
the ר"ן Ran talks about הלכתא hilcheta but I'm not going to
find it now.
Okay.
Fine. And so just to
sort of pull this together, so basically what we have to say
is a couple of things and just getting back to the חמץ
thing, right? Either you could say that no one needs to hear
me but everyone
knows.
If no one really knows that you did it or not, but
everyone thinks that you're going to do it or has a presumption
that you're going to do it already on shaky footing, right?
Okay, so what you're saying though that it would be enough for
חמץ even though if
it's all by yourself?
Yeah, because it's not really הפקר, no one says it's like full
הפקר.
Not getting into that now. It might that might be part of
that מחלוקת machlokes between תוספות and the רמב"ם Rambam is whether it
needs to be publicized in the same kind of a way or
not.
Not for now. But yeah, that's a good question. Okay, from here
we go on to מ"ה ע"ב. Mem Hey Amud Bet. It's a
new משנה Mishna. in a new פרק perek and it's a very
core סוגיא sugya of a very sticky and tricky topic. The topic
will be ברירה. breira. ברירה breira is a gigantic topic that covers
סוגיות sugyos I think in six or seven places across ש"ס Shas
with other repetitions of those גמרות Gemaras elsewhere as well. It touches
on גיטין, Gittin, in עירובין, Eruvin, here.
And the question is
can you say הוברר הדבר למפרע. huvar hadavar lemafrea. Can you say
that something happens later will now come retroactively clarify something I did
before. Two classic cases of ברירה breira that come from elsewhere and
then we'll deal with the case from our משנה. Mishna First case
of ברירה, breira, let's talk about separating out תרומה truma and מעשר.
maaser. Suppose I buy a barrel of wine and I want to
drink it but it's שבת. Shabbat. I'm not allowed to separate out
תרומה truma and מעשר maaser on שבת. Shabbat. So what do I
do?
I can say
whatever I'm leaving over at the end...
Exactly, whatever I leave behind in the bottom of the barrel and
I'll make sure to leave behind the right amount of wine, but
I'll say whatever remains in the bottom of the barrel will be
the תרומה truma and מעשר maaser and I designate them accordingly and
the rest of the wine should be חולין chullin and totally fine
for me to eat. Okay. So yeah, Charlie.
They probably shouldn't be separating tithes on שבת, Shabbat, it's a rabbinic
prohibition?
You're jumping the gun a little bit, but as you're asking the
question, we will note that at least להלכה lehalacha based on a
statement in ביצה, Beitzah,
we say יש ברירה yesh breira for rabbinic issues and we say
אין ברירה ein breira for biblical prohibitions. So we'll get back to
that in a second because the big מחלוקת machlokes is going to
be do we say יש ברירה, yesh breira, there is ברירה, breira,
we can employ this mechanism, or אין ברירה, ein breira, we cannot.
And the back and forth between many סוגיות sugyos is going to
be well this issue is kind of, it doesn't seem to fit
the model and then once we פסקן pasken that as a הלכה
that we say יש ברירה yesh breira for דרבנן derabanan and אין
ברירה ein breira for דאורייתא, then again getting the גמרא Gemara to
fit will get a little bit tricky.
If they start them, if they are written with them?
Okay, so we'll get into that as well. So ברירה, breira, so
the classic example, you have a barrel of wine, you designate the
תרומה truma and מעשר maaser in the bottom, and then you want
to drink the rest of the wine. Okay? So that's ברירה breira
because you're saying whatever is left at the end should retroactively have
been the wine that I separated out to begin with, meaning it
may have been that the wine was all mixing around throughout the
process. So that's an interesting question. Second example is from עירובי תחומין.
Eruvei Techumin. On שבת Shabbat you're not allowed to walk outside the
city.
It's either way, whichever way I go...
Well one second, I'm going to draw a picture
and we'll see because it's not you're not allowed to just סתם
stam do עירובי תחומין, Eruvei Techumin, you're not allowed to do it
just for fun. You could read the news, yes.
Are you in actuality separating that wine?
Well you don't know which wine is going to end up in
the bottom. It could be that the wine is mixing around throughout.
You never really separated it from the rest of the wine, it
remained mixed, and you said well when I get to the bottom,
then that wine that's left should have been the wine that I
tried to separate out and it was הוברר הדבר למפרע, huvar hadavar
lemafrea, it became clarified retroactively.
Okay, עירובי תחומין. Eruvei Techumin. I live in this city
and I don't know where the שיעור shiur is going to be
on שבת Shabbat afternoon. Is it going to be in this שול
shul or is it going to be in this שול? shul? So
I make two עירובי תחומין. Eruvei Techumin. I make one here,
that'll be my עירוב, eruv, and I'll make another עירוב eruv here.
And that means that I can now walk from between,
in this square because I can walk from this point into the
city and I can walk from this point to the שול. shul.
Or alternatively from here I would be able to walk from this
point to the שול shul and from this point back into the
city, I'd be able to get back to my house. So I
make two עירובין eruvin and I say, well I don't know where
the שיעור shiur is going to be. I want to go see
my רבי, the לשון of the סוגיא sugya there. So my רבי
is coming to town on שבת, Shabbat, I don't know which שול
shul he's speaking in, so I therefore set up two עירובי eruvei
and retroactively once I find out once they make the announcement on
Friday night in שול shul I find out which one is... where
he's going to be and retroactively I designate that that was the
עירוב Eruv that should have taken effect. In a certain sense this
is kind of like a תנאי. Tnai. תנאי Tnai making a conditional
statement, you could say well I make this עירוב Eruv on the
condition that my רבי would come to this שול Shul and כבר
בבא,
Kvar Bava, that was the first בבא Bava of the גמרא.
Gemara There are a lot of caveats, yes, there are a lot
of caveats and there are a lot of details that come into
it. Again, especially considering the fact that you can only make a
תנאי Tnai and make a שליח. Shaliach. The גמרא Gemara notes you
can only make a תנאי Tnai and make a שליח. Shaliach. Those
two things only apply to the same category for the most part:
making a תנאי Tnai and making a שליח, Shaliach,
and it seems like for this, not necessarily the right example. So
this is relying on ברירה Breira that retroactively it should become clarified
which עירוב Eruv I meant to make because I only made it
for the purpose of visiting my רבי. So those are two classic
examples of ברירה Breira and now we're going to see our משנה.
Mishna, Okay, so our משנה Mishna, says השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה.
Ha-shutafin she-nadru hana'ah zeh mi-zeh. Two people have a joint ownership of
land or of a, in this case a חצר. Chatzer. This is
a courtyard between their two apartment houses. So ראובן Reuven lives in
this apartment, שמעון Shimon lives here, and there's a חצר Chatzer in
between. They have joint ownership of the courtyard. You can imagine this
is like the hallway in a modern apartment building or something like
that. השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה. Ha-shutafin she-nadru hana'ah zeh mi-zeh. So
each of them took a נדר Neder against the other one to
not get any הנאה Hana'ah from each other. They really don't like
each other. Okay.
אסורין ליכנס לחצר. Asurin likanes le-chatzer. Therefore, neither of them can enter
the חצר. Chatzer. Why? Because the חצר Chatzer is owned jointly.
So if it's owned jointly, then ראובן Reuven owns part of the
חצר Chatzer that שמעון Shimon will be walking on and שמעון Shimon
owns part of the חצר Chatzer that ראובן Reuven will be walking
on. Therefore, since they each own the property jointly, that means they
each have some ownership of the property, and therefore it would be
problematic according to their נדר Neder for either of them to walk
in the חצר. Chatzer.
Okay. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס
לתוך שלו. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer: zeh nichnas le-toch shelo ve-zeh
nichnas le-toch shelo.
Okay. This one can enter into his part of the courtyard and
this one can enter into his part of the courtyard. What does
that mean? Okay, so this, at least according to what the גמרא
Gemara understands this part of the משנה, mishnah sounds like the חכמים
Chachamim hold
אין ברירה Ein breira because you cannot retroactively decide who owned which
part of the courtyard and רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov says, it sounds like יש ברירה. Yesh breira. Once you're walking
on it, you determine, it became clarified that that was the part
of the חצר Chatzer that you owned. Okay, so now here's the
question: how does שותפות Shutfus work? How does partnership work?
Does it mean I can walk all over or just like a
specific path?
You know what I mean? It sounds like לתוך שלו, le-toch shelo,
whatever the שלו shelo is. So the גמרא is going to discuss
what maybe there's if this is the חצר Chatzer and this is
the door of my house and this is the door of his
house, so he gets a certain amount of space around his door
and I get a certain amount of space around mine and maybe,
you know, how do we divide up the rest of the area
is the problem. So that's maybe part of this discussion is that
each of us gets a certain amount of לתוך שלו, le-toch shelo,
into each his own space in the communal space. This gets to
the core of what partnership is really like. If the two of
us own a field, is it,
imagine one person is the black stripes and one person is the
white stripes, is it alternating ownership? He owns this, he owns this,
he owns this, he owns this fully, each of them owns part
of it fully? Is the whole thing kind of a grey blur?
Every piece everyone owns a little bit of each share? Or is
there some way that we can sort of break it up plot
by plot, piece by piece, that each, you know, I could tiptoe
technically without doing anything? Even according to אין ברירה Ein breira maybe
parts of the field are each owned independently from each other. So
it could be grey, it could be a checkerboard black and white,
it could be stripes black and white, it could be one half
is white and one half is black so that those are two
totally separate pieces of land. That part of this question is what
is the partnership arrangement, or perhaps in general how does a partnership
ownership work? Okay.
As you can see, the רן is very long.
But before we get into
it, I guess I had a question. Like let's say we each
own like all the apartments in the חצר. Chatzer. So like then
are we allowed to go in?
I'm sorry, I don't exactly, in other
words it's not like, you know, you said this house and this
house, but let's say we enter the whole thing together.
Well exactly, that seems to be like what the חכמים Chachamim in
the first opinion in the משנה, Mishnah תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
saying. It sounds like the whole חצר Chatzer is owned jointly. Therefore,
there is no לתוך שלו le-toch shelo and לתוך שלו. le-toch shelo.
There's no way you can get around it. You own this whole
thing partially. I have a 50% share or I have a 20%
share in this property and therefore that's enough ownership to אסר assur
it according to anyone who can't get הנאה Hana'ah from me. And
alternatively, the
I'm stuck. There's no way around it. So that would be exactly
the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma rationale. The fact that רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov is saying, "Ah, you have an out,"
because if we say יש ברירה yesh breirah and maybe there's another
way to understand his position as well. But for at least for
now, saying יש ברירה yesh breirah sounds like, what does that mean?
That means once I'm walking on it, it, I can count it
as if this is the part that I own.
Do you need the other guy to say the same thing once
he walks on it?
Yeah, then נכנס לתוך שלו. nichnas l'toch shelo. Ah, נכנס לתוך שלו.
nichnas l'toch shelo. So that's the question. Can one person say well
this is mine and then switch it around and then you know
they want to use the same path? There's a path there. Right,
exactly. Exactly. So that's the question. So and that's why I wanted
to get into the רן. So the רן has a few different
explanations for how does this work because it doesn't seem like if
it's exactly. It doesn't even seem like it fits normal ברירה breirah
because like you're saying if it can kind of switch back and
forth well then it was never really clarified who owned it. It's
not like one time a person is going to walk through the
חצר chatzer and that's it. No, this is a piece of property
that's jointly owned. They each have competing claims that would forbid it
to each other. But the fact that they're kind of each going
through a little bit at a time, so are we just going
to say, we're not going to actually say it was clarified, בירר
הדבר, birer hadavar, it was actually clarified by some action retroactively? So
the first position is that well maybe walking isn't really הנאה. hana'ah.
Walking on the property really isn't הנאה. hana'ah. It's not real הנאה.
hana'ah. I want to get from place A to place B,
I want to get from place A to place B, I want
to put my feet down. Putting my feet on a piece of
land is not enough הנאה hana'ah that it really was forbidden by
the נדר.
neder. But if it was like a nice, you know, arbor, you
know, like
flowers and trees.
But that has nothing to do with ברירה breirah at all. Well,
it would at least soften to what it meaning, oh, what do
you mean it has nothing to do with ברירה? breirah? If it
still has to do with ברירה breirah because I'm still saying
that the walk on property that belongs to somebody that you're מודר
הנאה mudar hana'ah from then.
Okay, but so that would mean then that the נדר neder is
at least not מדאורייתא problem but this is some kind of rabbinic
construct about if you took a נדר neder הנאה hana'ah from someone,
also don't walk on his property. And therefore and that's some kind
of an extension. It's not real הנאה hana'ah but it's an extension,
and it's a furthered. Still doesn't see what it has to do
with ברירה. breirah. So then the ברירה breirah will still apply because,
okay, well then where I'm walking is then the ברירה breirah becomes
like רבי אלעזר בן יעקב's Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov position, it gives
me a loophole. I see what you're saying. Maybe the mechanism that
lets me walk.
Exactly. I'm going to have a very hard time understanding this משנה
Mishnah, having anything to do with ברירה.
breirah. Well we'll have to get to the גמרא in the next
few days.
But, so, I hear your question. Maybe it's not anything to do
with ברירה. breirah. If that's the case, if it's not really a
problem of the הנאה. hana'ah.
Why נכנס לתוך שלו nichnas l'toch shelo then?
If it's not הנאה hana'ah then there's no reason to. I was
in the middle of a sentence.
If it's if it's not really a problem of the הנאה, hana'ah,
then how would ברירה breirah help? It's not really a mechanism of
ברירה breirah because it's not saying like oh this part was fine
and this part would be forbidden. Michael had a question.
No, no, I'm saying and then there's no שלו shelo then, there's
no there's no then I'm saying then.
For sure.
Yeah, and again, that is a part of the debate as well.
That means the whole property
is as if it's regarding walking on it. That's true.
I'm sorry, Dov? Yeah. So Dov, I think רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam
point, which is quoted in this gigantic רן, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
makes a similar observation to what you're saying, which is that
it's really not because of יש ברירה. yesh breirah. This is something
else.
But the רמב"ן says maybe it's a different ברירה breirah than the
usual ברירה. breirah.
And the רן, so the רמב"ן is kind of saying of like
it's a weaker, a weaker ברירה breirah than usual because this is
kind of a strange case, it doesn't really fit. And the רן
says actually it's almost a stronger ברירה. breirah. Why? Because it was
already owned from known from the beginning who owned what. Meaning you're
not just saying I have a barrel of תרומה terumah now a
barrel of wine and I want to know which part is תרומה
terumah and which part is חולין. chullin. Now you're saying almost there
was an original partnership agreement between the two of us and then
once this issue came up it now clarifies. So there almost is
a sense that it really could be clarified from the beginning who
owns what in the partnership agreement. And that's kind of a sense
of you could really pin down this ברירה breirah very much. So
that's stronger than usual ברירה breirah and that's why it's different.
Wait even though it wasn't in the agreement that I own you
know the southeast part and you own the northwest part?
Well that's part of what this ברירה breirah means. ברירה breirah means
I'm retroactively retroactively clarifying what the original conditions were. But since there
was a real agreement, it's not just I have a barrel and
now I'm trying to to decide which part is going to be
תרומה, terumah, there was a real partnership. And so fine if we
want to now retroactively clarify the terms of the agreement, that would
actually be a stronger legal mechanism than a normal ברירה. breirah. Okay.
Fine. Yes.
Just touching on the on the wine of the barrel model, are
we conceptualizing this person during the course of the day walks only
50 percent of the property? or he walks all over 100 percent
of the property. Because at the end of the day,
if he's 100 percent of the property, then he was probably right
50 percent of the time. 50 percent of the property could have
been wrong. Right. I see.
That's part of what makes רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov's position so strange, and that's exactly what these ראשונים are struggling
with is that exactly that. That fine, if you want to really
say רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov יש ברירה, yesh
breira, that he's saying יש ברירה yesh breira and that it really
means whatever you walk on will be retroactively the part that you
had rights to, then I don't understand what you're saying exactly. Then
it will become a big problem if each of them walk on
the same place, or the parts overlap, or that they each use
the entire חצר. chatzer. So exactly, the next clause in the משנה
Mishnah says exactly that: ושניהם אסורים להעמיד ריחיים ותנור ולגדל תרנגולים. u-shneihem
assurim le-ha'amid reichayim ve-tannur u-legadel tarnagolim.
Both of them are prohibited from putting a millstone. This is like
the old-fashioned kind of millstone, not a big circular one that you
turn, but it's a big, big rock and you put a smaller
rock on top and you go back and forth. So that's the
millstone of the ריחיים. reichayim. The תורה has a special prohibition against
using the top millstone as a משכון, mashkon, as a collateral for
a loan, because if you confiscate the collateral, then the person can't
grind any food. They ground their wheat regular, even if they grind
the wheat once every two days or once every three days. So
fine, you won't be able to have any new flour, you won't
be able to bake bread. They didn't grind the, they ground the
flour fresh usually,
and so that would be a big problem. The תנור, tannur, the
ovens, they used to keep the ovens in the חצר chatzer because
their oven was like a clay tandoor oven. And so the oven
would be set up in the חצר, chatzer, and it would be
a communal use oven for everyone who lived in the חצר. chatzer.
So if one person starts to build a תנור tannur now in
the חצר, chatzer, but that's communal use. I cannot use anything or
create anything that, number one, is occupying a permanent space in the
חצר. chatzer. For example, the ריחיים, reichayim, excuse me, the ריחיים reichayim
and the תנור tannur would sit there permanently. So maybe that's the
problem, that it occupies a space in the חצר. chatzer. Or alternatively,
it's that this is a public use thing, and I've now introduced
something to the חצר chatzer which someone else will not be allowed
to get benefit from, but the terms of ownership are that he
would be allowed to get benefit from it because it's in the
חצר. chatzer. You can't just say that it's forbidden for him to
use the oven, and that would be a conflict between the נדר
neder and
the ownership agreement regarding use of the חצר, chatzer, not necessarily the
implementation therein.
But that's sort of the standard use of the חצר chatzer is
that whatever gets set up in the חצר chatzer is for everyone
to use.
Right, so that's understood,
but then you can argue and say... The גמרא will go into
that exactly, some of those questions.
And להעמיד le-ha'amid difference that use,
so להעמיד le-ha'amid just means to put it there, construct de novo.
But what if it's already there?
So that I think comes up as well, which is what if
there's already, meaning that sort of falls into the category of using
the חצר. chatzer. If it's already there, that's part of the חצר.
chatzer. To now build a new oven becomes part of then you're
also using the חצר chatzer as a space to now do a
construction project. And a third example, לגדל תרנגולים, legadel tarnagolim, to grow
chickens. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi here raises an issue about raising chickens. Well,
some of the issues of זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh
ve-zeh lo chaseir. What if one person is getting benefit from the,
if even if it's one person's chickens, like you know whose chickens
they are, and the chickens are using the חצר, chatzer, but it's
not anyone else's detriment to have chickens running around in the חצר?
chatzer? That's just a normal thing. So maybe there, you know, who's
getting הנאה hana'ah from whom? Who's, is it really detracting from his
use of the חצר chatzer or not? That comes up in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well and the בבלי Bavli here.
Well, chickens are different than
people.
Well, chickens are your property. You own the chickens, and the chickens
are now running around using the חצר chatzer as their chicken coop.
Right, but you're saying זה נהנה וזה לא חסר, zeh neheneh ve-zeh
lo chaseir, so why is the other person חסר? chaseir?
So I didn't see that inside recently. It was a little while
ago, the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which was for a totally different project. I
really wasn't focused on understanding how it fits with this משנה, Mishnah,
so I'll have to go back and check. I'll check for tomorrow.
Okay,
fine.
היה אחד מהם מודר הנאה מחבירו.
haya echad me-hem mud-dar hana'ah mi-chavero. But they can't be לגדל תרנגולים
legadel tarnagolim because why? Because it's because it's using my part of
the חצר. chatzer.
Either because the chickens are going to run around the whole thing,
and therefore I can never say whatever the chicken is walking on
is always was my part to begin with, because they'll occupy the
whole space. Or possibly because allowing chickens into the חצר chatzer will
be me getting a certain הנאה hana'ah from the property. Either it's
getting הנאה hana'ah from the property of the other person, that if
ראובן Reuven owns the chickens and שמעון Shimon, is now forbid him
to get הנאה hana'ah from his property, so then for ראובן Reuven
to put his chickens into the חצר chatzer will be inappropriate use
of the חצר. chatzer. Or alternatively, it may be actually that the
chickens become part of the problem, that somehow the chickens being there,
even if it's part of the normal use of the חצר, chatzer,
the fact that now I've set up sort of almost a communal
in the communal space, just like the problem of the oven and
the ריחיים, reichayim, that putting something of communal use into the חצר
chatzer would be
a
problem.
Right, that everyone will get shares of the eggs that the chickens
lay and things like that. It’s a possibility, I’m not for sure.
Okay, second case in the משנה Mishnah, is now not that both
took a נדר neder against each other, but now היה אחד מהם
מודר הנאה מחברו. haya echad mehem mudar hana'ah michaveiro. One person has
forbidden the other. So it’s only one directional נדר. neder. So now
how does it apply? לא יכנס לחצר. lo yikanes lachatzer.
He, meaning the person who was מודר הנאה, mudar hana'ah, the person
who was forbidden, cannot enter the חצר chatzer at all.
That fits the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. No, I don’t like that
at all. Why? You know, I mean he... I own fifty percent
of it. You can't forbid me to go into my... I own
at least part of it.
Because every... every piece of land is jointly owned.
Every fleck
of dirt is jointly owned. And this person forbid you to get
any benefit from his fifty percent share, so then there is no
place that is not... contain a piece of his.
Yeah, but you can’t forbid me to use my own thing.
Ah, okay, so
אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, ein adam oser davar she’eino shelo,
but it’s also fifty percent mine.
So how can that work? So again, that becomes almost... is a
problematic... the balance between on the one hand תנא קמא’s Tanna Kamma
position in the first משנה, Mishnah in the first clause of the
משנה, Mishnah makes a lot of sense.
Fine, they each אסר aser'd it against each other. This now problematizes
the תנא קמא’s Tanna Kamma position.
Yeah, I like...
here I see רבי אלעזר בן יעקב’s Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov position
makes a lot more sense. Meaning, how can a person say this...
you know, the only way to get into my house and now
someone has אסר aser'd it to me even though I owned partial
rights to that property. That’s exactly.
What does he do then? So what... does he have to... like...
So רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says לתוך שלי
אני נכנס. l'toch sheli ani nichnas. I’m going into mine.
What’s the תנא קמא... Tanna Kamma... what is he...
We’re going to have to get into...
He’s going to force him to buy me out, but then he’s
giving me הנאה hana'ah by buying me out.
We’re going to get into all of that, I’m sure we’ll do
a bit more about that tomorrow. I just want to try to
finish the משנה Mishnah today. We’re going to go back and deal...
because this is now many more pieces of data. You know, the
משנה mishna. on the first עמוד is only three lines. So we
have a few more... a little bit more to go. Okay.
Can I just... Sure. I was thinking it’s possible we’re talking about
where... where partner A says I forswear הנאה hana'ah from partner B.
That way, then it’s easy to understand how he, you know, does
it to himself basically.
Ah, okay, so that’s a possibility. So we’ll see exactly the way
the משנה mishna. follows up, which is exactly Michael’s point. So we
see here: יכול לומר לו לתוך שלי אני נכנס. yachol lomar lo
l'toch sheli ani nichnas.
I’m going into my part, ואיני נכנס לתוך שלך, v'eini nichnas l'toch
shelcha, I’m not going into yours. And וכופין את הנודר למכור חלקו.
v'kofin et hanoder limkor chelko.
We force the נודר noder who forbid the public access to the
person’s apartment to sell his rights to it and therefore it would
be now permitted for him to go at least along the part
that he needs.
But to somebody else, right? Does he have to sell it to...
to me?
He’s still... to me. He can sell it now... me. He can
sell it to whomever. He can sell it to whomever, because that
would then remove the איסור issur because the איסור issur is dependent
on his ownership.
Again, if he sells it to me, you’re מהנה mahaneh me and
you took on a... now...
No, he’s not selling it to me. He’s selling it to someone.
Either he’s selling it to the corporate... he’s selling it either to
a third party or selling it to a corporation.
I understand that. Does he sell to me then?
Presumably not, presumably not.
Yeah, but until he does, I mean what am I supposed to...
you know... He doesn’t have to sell it to you. He can
sell it to whomever because then it won’t be forbidden.
No, but until he sells it though, according to... according to that...
Well, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says two points.
Number one, he can always say, he can use ברירה b'reira as
a mechanism to say לתוך שלי אני נכנס. l'toch sheli ani nichnas.
I’m going into mine, and therefore I’m not violating the נדר neder
at all. And even if we think that that’s fishy,
so again, that clause about כופין אותו, kofin oto, forcing him to
sell it. Does that apply to the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? It
definitely applies to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. The question is whether
it applies to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov or
not.
Right, so it applies to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
though, what does he do until then? That’s... Well, but that’s part
of the point which is maybe תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, like you
were saying, if the question is whether we can say אין אדם
אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo, a person
cannot forbid something which doesn’t belong to them, so how can this
person even have set up the situation to begin with? The fact
that תנא קמא Tanna Kamma thinks that this is allowed to begin
with has created now a tricky situation, but we might not necessarily
force him to get rid of it. Meaning, it’s in something he
had the right to do that. Again, this is something similar to
the other example, a big classic problem with שותפים. shutafim. What if
two partners own a slave, and then one of them frees the
slave, so is this person חציו עבד חציו בן חורין? chatzyo eved
chatzyo ben chorin? A person is half slave and half free. A
free person is not allowed to marry a slave and a slave
is not allowed to marry a free woman, and therefore the person
would not be allowed to marry anyone, and therefore we say even
according to the opinion that he is such a person as חציו
עבד חציו בן חורין, chatzyo eved chatzyo ben chorin, we force the
other master to free him. Okay, you have a question Mike?
No, I was going to say that. Because it’s a
person and... לבטל לו מפריה ורביה. l'batel lo mi'periyah v'reviyah.
Okay, right.
So we have בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and that comes... Okay, fine. So that was the case. כופין את
הנודר למכור את חלקו. kofin et hanoder limkor et chelko. We force
the person who made the נדר neder to sell his portion. האחד
מן השוק מודר באחד מהן הנאה. ha'echad min hashuk mudar be'echad mehen
hana'ah. What if someone else, someone who lives outside the חצר chatzer
takes a נדר neder to not get any benefit from either of
them?
Okay, מודר הנאה, mudar hana'ah,
מודר באחד מהן mudar be'echad mehen from one of them. לא יכנס
לחצר. lo yikanes lachatzer. So he also cannot enter the חצר chatzer
and he doesn't have any kind of rights to this חצר chatzer
to begin with. He just said, okay fine, I'm not getting הנאה.
hana'ah. So this is again saying the ownership of the חצר chatzer
is a joint ownership.
ראובן Reuven owns, you know, 10% share of the חצר chatzer and
therefore someone from out in the street, לוי, took a נדר neder
to not get anything from ראובן, Reuven, well, he also can't come
into the חצר chatzer because every spot that he walks on would
be a part that ראובן Reuven owns. Okay, fine. לא יכנס לחצר.
lo yikanes lachatzer.
ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר verabbi eliezer ben yaakov omer יכול לומר
לתוך של חברך אני נכנס ואיני נכנס לתוך שלך. yachol lomar letoch
shel chavercha ani nichnas ve'eini nichnas letoch shelcha. That once again...
Does the friend doesn't mind that he's trespassing?
Well again, this is acting on the question of public use of
land or acceptable use of land. If you have your front yard,
you know, can people walk on your front yard? Can people walk
in the alleyway behind your house? Can people use the חצר? chatzer?
Well, the חצר chatzer of the apartment building is owned jointly by
the people, tenants of the apartment building. Question is whether someone from
the outside can use the חצר chatzer or not. You know, people
like to put a double door on their apartment building to keep
random people from walking in.
So that part of the question. Can he rely on that or
not? Does it become a question of trespass? Okay. המודר הנאה מחברו
hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro ויש לו מרחץ ובית הבד. veyesh lo merchatz uveit
habad. A person says, I can't get הנאה hana'ah from you, he
takes a נדר neder to not get any הנאה hana'ah from, so
ראובן Reuven says he won't get any הנאה hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon
and שמעון Shimon owns a bathhouse, מרחץ merchatz ובית הבד, uveit habad,
an olive press.
Okay.
מושכרים בעיר. mushcharim ba'ir. מושכרים בעיר, mushcharim ba'ir, that they are a
rentable space, you can hire it out in the city. אם יש
לו בהן תפיסת יד, im yesh lo bahen tefisat yad, if he
has
a
certain sense of access... we'll get back to this tomorrow. אסור, assur,
then it's forbidden because the fact that he has some kind of
rights to it. Meaning that שמעון Shimon as the owner of the
olive press has a certain, even once it has been rented out
to whomever wants to use it, he can still exercise some residual
rights over it, right?
What do you mean by אם יש לו בהן תפיסת יד? im
yesh lo bahen tefisat yad?
Meaning that שמעון Shimon owns the olive press and now he rents
it out to someone to press their olives. Okay. But now שמעון
Shimon, shows up and he says, I want to kick you out,
or I want to... like different kinds of residual ownership even once
it has been rented out. He has תפיסת יד, tefisat yad, he
has a certain residual...
If he does or if the owner does?
If he does, אי, i, right? It says, right?
What does it mean? אי? i?
Only because there're two possibility, there are two possibilities... so the possibilities
of the rental agreement could be either... we'll touch on it more
tomorrow because we're basically done with the משנה.
mishna, What do you mean ownership? You use that word, if you
rent something, you still own the thing you rent. For sure. So
what do you mean by residual?
That's what I was saying.
Maybe residual ownership is the wrong word, but that he has certain
rights even during the period of rental. He has certain kinds of
use rights. Okay. And we'll touch on it definitely more tomorrow because
that will be our main topic. I just wanted to kind of
go through the משנה. mishna. So if he has תפיסת יד, tefisat
yad, let's leave it untranslated for now, תפיסת יד, tefisat yad, אסור.
assur. אין לו בהן תפיסת יד, ein lo bahen tefisat yad, if
he doesn't have that kind of use rights while someone else has
already rented his property, then he cannot... then there's no more איסור
issur because not really his. That's the exact point. Maybe it is
something like almost like an ownership. How do we treat this שכירות?
sechirus? How do we treat the rental? Does the rental really remove
it from my ownership to the point where the נדר neder no
longer applies or not?
Okay.
So if he doesn't...
אין לו בהן תפיסת יד, ein lo bahen tefisat yad, מותר. mutar.
Then if he doesn't have those use rights, then מותר, mutar, then
the נדר neder would not apply to that property.
So he can't... he can't אסור assur it because it's rented out
to the other guy?
It's rented out to the other person, so it's really no longer
in my רשות, it's no longer under my control and so therefore
it wouldn't be a problem. האומר לחברו קונם לביתך שאני נכנס. ha'omer
lachaveiro konam leveitcha she'ani nichnas.
So a person says to his friend, ראובן Reuven says to שמעון,
my house is אסור assur to you that you don't enter. Okay,
so that's one kind of נדר. neder. You said assur to me
that I won't enter. Sorry, קונם לביתך שאני נכנס. konam leveitcha she'ani
nichnas. Right.
Your house is אסור assur to me that I won't enter. ובשדך
שאני לוקח, uvesadecha she'ani loke'ach,
or your field is אסור assur that I do not take from
your produce. מת או שמכרו לאחר, met o shemacharo le'acher, if he
dies or if he sold it to someone else... this was a
proof text, a משנה, mishna. proof text we used a few, what,
about two weeks ago
in the discussion of what can get you out of the נדר.
neder. What if you made a נדר? neder?
I make a נדר neder only from my property, right? We had
the מחלוקת machloket about whether that applies to property, but once you
sell the property then it gets out of the נדר neder or
not? So this was a proof for one of the sides of
the מחלוקת, machloket, this משנה. mishna. Okay. משנה. mishna Okay. משנה. mishna
קונם konam
בית זה bayit ze שאני נכנס. she'ani nichnas. בית זה. bayit ze.
He didn't say ביתך. beitcha. בית זה. bayit ze. This house, not
your house. Right? That was exactly the point. Did you mean to
say that it's only while it's my property that the נדר neder
should apply? But if I sell it, well then it would be
מותר. muttar. קונם konam בית זה, bayit ze, this house, not your
house, right? That was exactly the point. Did you mean to say
that it's only while it's my property that the נדר neder should
apply? But if I sell it, well then it would be fine?
Or are you really saying this object becomes אסור? assur? So this
משנה became an important text for that מחלוקת. machloket. So קונם konam
בית זה, bayit ze, this house is אסור, assur, שאני נכנס, she'ani
nichnas, that I won't go into it. שדה זו sadeh zo שאני
לוקח she'ani lokeach מת או שמכרו לאחר met o she-macharo l'acher אסור.
assur. So even after he dies and it goes to his יורש,
yoresh, or if he sells it, then it remains forbidden. So with
that, we're going to touch on this משנה again tomorrow and we'll
go forward on מ"ו. mem vav. So just to... yes, question.
This would seem to have application to modern public corporations that are
run by a bunch of people and you are part of it.
So for instance, most public companies do business on שבת. Shabbat. By
the rabbis, that would seem to be a problem. But by the
מנחת יצחק, Minchat Yitzchak,
this would seem to not be a problem because your fraction is
never going to be... is rarely going to be... חמץ on פסח,
Pesach, too.
Yeah, there are a number of תשובות, teshuvot, I think at least
for sure I can remember off the top of my head that
in one of the מלמד להועיל Melamed LeHo'il that David Zvi Hoffman
has a תשובה teshuvah about corporate ownership of חמץ on פסח in
the case of a beer brewery. The question of corporations and הלכה
is one that's very interesting, very important.
Corporations didn't exist at this time. Exactly.
Right. Is there a corporate entity distinct from each of the individual
owners? If the corporation exists and we buy shares of the profit
that the corporation will earn, or are we really all partners, human
partners in an agreement for the profit that comes in? And that
exactly gets into the question: can there be corporate ownership? Can there
be for חמץ on פסח, for שבת? Shabbat? Those are really...
what constitutes a Jewish corporation? Or is there...